Guide to the Alice Walsh Sunset Park collection CBHM.0005
Center for Brooklyn History
Alice Walsh Sunset Park collection
circa 1910-circa 2010
Center for Brooklyn History
Sunset Park Restoration Committee
Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company
CBHM.0005
0.63 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and one half manuscript box.
This collection includes materials gathered by Alice Walsh, Sunset Park resident and former president of the Sunset Park Restoration Committee: photographic negatives and prints depicting the construction of the 4th Avenue subway line and materials related to the activities of the Sunset Park Restoration Committee.
Scope and Contents
The Alice Walsh Sunset Park collection, circa 1910-circa 2010, includes materials gathered by Alice Walsh, Sunset Park resident and former president of the Sunset Park Restoration Committee. The photographic negatives and prints taken by the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company in the early 1900s, depict the construction of the 4th Avenue subway line. Other photographs and negatives from the early 1900s depict Bush Terminal, Victory Gardens, the Sunset Park waterfront, and Brooklyn Army Terminal and were used in Sunset Park: A Time Remembered by Robert J. Walsh and Alice Walsh and published by the Sunset Park Restoration Committee in 1980. The Sunset Park Restoration Committee materials include house tour brochures, correspondence, photographs, event flyers, and an education curriculum.
Biographical Note
Alice Walsh has been a resident of Sunset Park for over 40 years and is a co-founder of the Sunset Park Restoration Committee. She served as the Committee's first president from 1976 - 1980. During Walsh's time as president, the Sunset Park Restoration Committee received a grant from the Brooklyn Educational and Cultural Alliance (BECA) to produce a 20 minute film about Sunset Park. Walsh co-wrote the book, Sunset Park: A time remembered with Robert J. Walsh.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series 1: 4th Avenue subway construction photographs, 1910-1915
Series 2: Sunset Park Restoration Committee records, circa 1910-circa 2010
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alice Walsh, 2021.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The majority of the materials in this collection are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact cbhreference@bklynlibrary.org at least two weeks prior to research visit.
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Center for Brooklyn History holds the following related materials:
- Sunset Park: A time remembered, Robert J. Walsh and Alice Walsh, 1980 (F129.B7 W35 1980 c.2)
- Brooklyn neighborhood associations and civic organizations publications, 1881-2010 (ARC.167)
- Tide-Water Building Company Collection, 1910-1919 (2007.018)
- Brooklyn railroad and subway collection, 1853-1958 (ARC.152)
- Subway Construction photographs on Brooklyn Public Library's digital collections.
Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Transportation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Subways -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Design and construction; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- New York -- History; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Neighborhood Associations; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Sunset Park Restoration Committee; Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company
- Series 1: 4th Avenue subway construction photographs, 1910-1915
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1: 4th Avenue subway construction photographs, 1910-1915, includes photographic prints and negatives taken during the building of the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's 4th Avenue subway line. The images depict residences, storefronts, and churches along 4th Avenue, as well as the construction. Each image includes the address depicted and the date the image was captured.
  Custodial History
  Prior to the 2021 gift to Center for Brooklyn History, the negatives from the building of the 4th Avenue subway line were found in a drawer in the MTA's offices by Mike Rochford and Frank Goldsmith and given to Alice Walsh and Robert J. Walsh in the 1970s.
  Historical Note
  The 4th Avenue subway line was built by the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company (BRT). This project was part of the Dual Contracts agreement between the New York City government and the Interborough Rapid Transit Company (IRT) and signed in 1913. The line opened in 1915. The BRT was acquired by the Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Corporation (BMT) in 1923 after the BRT went bankrupt.
  Arrangement
  The series is in original order.
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 4th Avenue subway line construction, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series 2: Sunset Park Restoration Committee records, circa 1910-circa 2010; 1980-1989
  The series is in chronological order.
  The Sunset Park Restoration Committee was formed in 1976 by residents who wanted to represent Sunset Park at the annual Brooklyn Brownstone Fair. During the late 1970s and 1980s, the Committee sponsored house tours, home improvement workshops, flea markets, square dances, and an educational history guide and walking tour for 4th graders. The Sunset Park Restoration Committee has also advocated for historic district status for areas of the neighborhood and publishes informational material about the history and current activities of the neighborhood.
  Series 2: Sunset Park Restoration Committee records, circa 1910-circa 2010, includes House Tour brochures, event flyers, and an educational curriculum developed for local schools. The curriculum was funded by a 1981 Brooklyn Educational and Cultural Alliance grant and developed by the Prospect Park Environmental Center and the Environmental Action Coalition. This series also includes photographs that were included in Sunset Park: A time remembered, researched and written by Robert J. Walsh and Alice Walsh, and published by the Sunset Park Restoration Committee in 1980.
  - Sunset Park waterfront negatives, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sunset Park waterfront photograph, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brooklyn Veterans Hospital, Fort Hamilton, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Monthly Messenger advertisements negatives, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Norwegian Lutheran Deaconesses' Home and Hospital photograph, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Victory Garden negative, circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sunset Park and Bay Ridge landmarks, circa 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Community History and Environmental Education curriculum, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - House and Garden Tour materials, 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - List of activities and accomplishments, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - House and Garden Tour photographs, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sunset Park information booklet, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Community history education brochure, circa 1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sunset Park Restoration Committee 10th anniversary flyer, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Historic district anniversary invitation, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sunset Arts Council events flyers, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sunset Park Landmarks Committee brochure, circa 2010 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - News clipping, circa 2010 (Box 2, Folder 7)